<page label="Screenshots" title="ICING Screenshots" prev="index" next="basics" jsfile="../screenshots.js">

	<h1>Screenshots</h1>


    <p>
                Click on an image for a larger version; click again to close.
        </p>


        <screenshot no="1" zi="20">
        <h3>Cells and channels</h3>
        <p>
	         The main display shows the contents of the model folder on the far left. The
	         selected morphology is shown in the middle with details of the selected cell properties
	         specification (one or more channel populations) at the bottom.
        </p>
        </screenshot>


   <screenshot no="2" zi="19">
        <h3>Discretization</h3>
        <p>
	           As well as the channels, the effect of a given discretization parameter can also
	           be shown on the morphology. This is independent of any channel allocation: the channels
	           are positioned on the cell according to the supplied distribution rules and only allocated
	           to compartments when the calculation is run with a particular spatial resolution.
        </p>
        </screenshot>

   <screenshot no="3" zi="18">
        <h3>Channel display</h3>
        <p>
             In the standard view, channels are shown as dots or circles depending on the scale. The structure
             can be moved, resized and rotated with the mouse.
        </p>
        <p>
        	Depending on the zoom factor, not all the channels are shown. The display keeps
        	the same color intensity independent of the scale, so if the corresponding channel
        	size is less than one pixel, then only a subset of channels is shown.
        </p>
        </screenshot>
   <screenshot no="4" zi="17">
        <h3>Region labelling</h3>
        <p>
              All the normal PSICS channel distribution options are available through the user interface.
              In particular, labels attached to the morphology can be used as part of the specification
              for region constraints. Here channels are applied uniformly to all parts of the cell distal
              to label1. The labels can be pulled off and re-attached with the mouse.
        </p>
        </screenshot>

           <screenshot no="5" zi="16">
        <h3>Distribution specification</h3>
        <p>
             Both the density and region specifications can contain expressions. Here channels are applied
             to five micron segments of dendrite every 20 micron with the "(p % 20) &lt; 5" condition.
        </p>
        </screenshot>

           <screenshot no="6" zi="15">
        <h3>3D Visualization</h3>
        <p>
	           As well as the projection view, a shaded 3D view can be opened in a separate window.
	           The pan, zoom and roll controls are the same.
        </p>
        </screenshot>

           <screenshot no="7" zi="14">
        <h3>3D Channels</h3>
        <p>
          Each channel has an exact position on the cell.
        </p>
        </screenshot>


           <screenshot no="8" zi="13">
        <h3>Display styles</h3>
        <p>
              Three levels of display resolution are available depending on the available memory and
              graphics hardware.
        </p>
        </screenshot>

           <screenshot no="9" zi="12">
        <h3>High resolution channels</h3>
        <p>
             The most detailed display can require many millions of triangles to show all the
             channels on the cell. This may give poor interactive performance for the
             whole cell, though smaller sections of the cell can typically be manipulated without
             trouble.
        </p>
        </screenshot>


</page>