<page label="Bibliography" prev="utilities" next="../formats/index">

	<h1>Bibliography</h1>

	<par>
		Under development...
	</par>

 	<h2>Numerical methods for stochastic processes</h2>


 	<pbib>Cao Y, Li H and Petzold, L
	<a name="cao" href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus&amp;list_uids=15332951">Efficient
	 formulation of the stochastic simulation algorithm for chemically reacting systems.</a>
	J Chem Phys, Vol. 121, No. 9. (1 September 2004), pp. 4059-4067.
 	</pbib>


 	<pindent>
 		Summary of various stochastic simulation algorithms for chemical systems and a discussion of their efficiency.
 	</pindent>




 	<pbib>Kim T. Blackwell
 	<a name="blackwell" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jneumeth.2006.04.003">An
 		efficient stochastic diffusion algorithm for modeling second messengers in
 		dendrites and spines</a> Journal of Neuroscience Methods
Volume 157, Issue 1, 15 October 2006, Pages 142-153
 	</pbib>
 	<pindent>
 		<i>Reaction-diffusion systems using a tau-leap style method and lookup tables.</i>
 	</pindent>
 	<pindent>
	ABSTRACT: Intracellular signaling pathways, which encompass both biochemical
	 reactions and second messenger diffusion, interact non-linearly
	  with neuronal membrane properties in their role as essential
	  intermediaries for synaptic plasticity and neuromodulation. Computational
	   modeling is a productive approach for investigating these phenomena;
	    however, most current strategies for modeling neurons exclude
	     signaling pathways. To overcome this deficiency, a new algorithm
	     is presented to simulate stochastic diffusion in a highly efficient
	     manner. The gain in speed is obtained by considering collections of
	     molecules, instead of tracking the movement of individual molecules.
	     The probability of a molecule leaving a spatially discrete
	      compartment is used to create a lookup table that stores the
	       probability of km molecules leaving the compartment as a function
	        of the total number of molecules in the compartment. During the
	        simulation, the number of molecules leaving the compartment is
	         determined using a uniform random number as an index into the
	         lookup table. Simulations illustrate the accuracy of this algorithm
	          by comparing it with the theoretical solution for deterministic
	           diffusion. Additional simulations show how spines on a dendritic
	           branch compartmentalize diffusible molecules. The efficiency of
	           the algorithm is sufficient to allow simulation of second messenger
	           pathways in a multitude of spines on an entire neuron.

 	</pindent>


	<h2>Voltage propagation on trees</h2>
	<pbib>
	Hines, M. <a name="hines1" href="http://www.neuron.yale.edu/ftp/neuron/papers/effic84.pdf">Efficient
	computation of branched nerve equations. (PDF)</a>
	Int. J. Bio-Med. Comput. 15:69-76, 1984
	</pbib>

	<pindent>
	   Describes the differenceing scheme used in Neuron, and in particular, the efficient
	   voltage propagation method.
	</pindent>


</page>
