<page label="Utilities" prev="fortran" next="biblio">

	<h1>Utilities</h1>

	<par>
		A wide variety of external tools are available that can be used to define the inputs
		and process the output of PSICS. This section lists tools that can be useful in this context
		but is by no means an exhaustive list.
	</par>


	<h2>Model specifications - creating XML files</h2>

	<h3>Emacs + XML Lite</h3>
		<par>
			Emacs provides a number of ways for editing XML files, of which
			<a href="http://wttools.sourceforge.net/emacs-stuff/emacsandxml.html">xml-lite mode</a> is
			a good choice for the small files needed by PSICS. It handles tag matching and indentation without
			the complexity of requireing a schema or DTD.
		</par>


	<h3>Smultron (Mac OSX)</h3>
		<par>
		Availabel free from <a href="http://smultron.sourceforge.net/">smultron.sourceforge.net</a>,
		"Smultron is a free text editor for Mac OS X Leopard 10.5 which is both easy to
		use and powerful. It is designed to not confuse newcomers nor disappoint advanced users.".
	</par>

	<h3>Eclipse</h3>
		<par>
			There are numerous XML editing plugins for <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse</a>, an interactive
			development environment designed for software developers but that can be used writing many other types of
			content, including PSICS models. The default XML editor provides syntax checking and formatting.
		</par>


	<h2>Simple visualization</h2>

		<par>
			The two programs dview.jar and ccviz.jar are linked from the downloads page and
			provide a quick way to view the outputs of PSICS. They can be useful for checking
			the results before using more sophisticated tools.
		</par>

	<h3>DView</h3>
	<par>
		Model specification files can include optional "ViewConfig" blocks that are used by PSICS to generate
		plots for the default summary pages. These can also be loaded in a stand-alone viewer,
		<a href="../dview.jar">DView</a>, which is part of <a href="http://www.catacomb.org/">Catacomb</a>. The viewer
		supports panning and zooming to examine details of the results. Like PSICS it is an executable jar file.
		It be run with <br/>
		<cmd> java -jar dview.jar viewfile.xml</cmd>
	</par>


	<h3>CCViz</h3>
	<par>
			Another stand-alone Catacomb component, <a href="../ccviz.jar">CCViz</a> can read and display the
			discretized cell structure that is generated whenever a PSICS model is run.
	</par>


	<h2>Analysis and visualization</h2>
	<par>
		TBD - info about reading output in IGOR Pro, Matlab, Yorick etc.
	</par>



</page>
