<page label="Ion Channels" prev="environment" next="properties">

	<h1>Ion Channels</h1>

	<par>
		The KSChannel object encompasses all the allowed formats for ion channel definitions. The "KS" prefix
		indicates that it is focused on kinetic schemes, but it also allows multi-complex channels which enables
		Hodgkin-Huxley style models to be included within the same formalism. A single complex scheme is one where
		any state is connected to all other states directly or indirectly by channel transitions. A multi-complex scheme
		is one where the states fall into disjoint groups, or gating complexes. Each gating complex behaves independently
		and the relative conductance of the whole channel is the product of the relative conductances of each complex.
		A typical Hodgkin-Huxley model has three or four independent two-state complexes.
	</par>
	<par>
		For stochastic calculations, multi-complex schemes are internally converted to the equivalent
		single-complex scheme. For deterministic calculations either form may be used, depending which is more efficient.
		Further details on the stochastic channel algorithm can be found in the <a href="../guide/methods.html">numerical
		methods</a> section of the user guide.
	</par>

	<par>
		A channel is specified as a collection of states and transitions.
		There are two types of state, <x>OpenState</x> or <x>ClosedState</x>, and rather more types of transition.
		Each state should have an id that is unique within the channel definition. The transitions then refer to states
		by this id in their <x>from</x> and <x>to</x> attributes specifying the start and end states.
		There are a number of different parameterizations provided for the transitions themselves, but in general models
		should use the <x>VHalfTransition</x> for all voltage-dependent transitions. The other transition types are
		provided so that PSICS can exactly express certain legacy channel models for validation purposes but do not
		necessarily have much biophysical justification.
	</par>

	<par>
		For multi-complex channels, the states and transitions for each complex should be embedded within KSComplex
		objects. This is not strictly required (PSICS can work out what the sub-complexes are just from the
		transition start and end points) but is good practice. It <i>is</i> required if there are multiple instances of
		a certain complex and you do not want to list all the states and transitions explicitly. In that case you can define
		them once and set the <x>instances</x> attribute to say how many instances of the complex there are in the
		channel. This is primarily useful for representing Hodgkin-Huxley style models where the powers on the gating
		variables can be interpreted as the number of instances of a two-state gate.

	</par>



	<TypeSetRef title="Ion Channels" ref="ChannelComponents"/>

</page>