<page label="Standards" prev="units" next="../icing/index">


	<h1>Input specifications and emerging standards</h1>

	<par>
		Emerging standards for cell morphology, MorphML,  and ion channels, ChannelML,
		are partially supported for the specification of models for PSICS. In general,
		most MorphML morphologies can be used as they are, and the majority of ChannelML files for
		voltage gated channels are compatible subject to the assumption of a default single-channel
		conductance.
	</par>



	<par>
		More details of the current status of NeorML imports in PSICS and
		suggestions for ways to improve compatibility can be found in
		 a spearate section: <a href="../neuroml/index.html">Importing NeuroML</a>.
	</par>


	<par>
		ChannelML files that specify models with concentration dependent gating, as in calcium activated
		potassium channels, cannot be used since PSICS cannot currently compute such models.
	</par>
	<par>
		Some ChannelML files can express models that can be computed by PSICS but that cannot be imported
		automatically. These are mainly HH-style models with extended or ad-hoc specifications of rate equations
		beyond the standard alpha/beta (forward rate, reverse rate) or tau/inf (time constant and eqilibrium
		open fraction) forms. Such models generally <i>can</i> be computed by PSICS, since it supports
		arbitrary coded transitions, but the conversion is not
		automatic. It is likely to be more effective to convert the relatively small number of such models
		by hand, rather than developing a general solution for importing them.
	</par>

	<par>
		The kinetic scheme structures in ChannelML are relatively close to those used in PSICS, and
		the standard fitted transition types (sigmoid, exponential, etc) can be imported. The default
		biophysical transition parameterization used in PSICS is not specifically supported although
		it can be expressed as a generic equation.
		Since any voltage-gated channel models can be expressed as compound kinetic schemes, the kinetic
		scheme elements (ks_gate) of ChannelML provide the cleanest export route for PSICS models, although
		they are note widely supported by other systems yet.
	</par>

</page>